Finding Aid for Media Resources Center (University of Michigan) films and videotapes, 1930s and 1948-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Series H, Michigan Report
  - Design and the American Consumer 1954, 851831-H-24; A look at a model kitchen designed for use and study by delegates to a campus conference sponsored by UM and the Institute of Contemporary Art of Boston. Features: Aare K. Lahti, UM-Arch.; Eric Larrabee, Harper's Mag.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #38, Pos. #632
  - Respirator Center, University Hospital 1954, 851831-H-25; Director of the UM Hospital Respirator Center and Supt. of Social Services discuss work in rehabilitation of polio patients at UM Hospital. [from kinescope neg. section of pos. film that was spliced into print is missing, sound quality is poor] Features: David Dickinson, UM-Hosp.; Ruth Loker, UM-Hosp.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #40
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 11)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-H25.flv
  - UM Bands 1955, 851831-H-26; A behind the scenes look at rehearsal of UM Marching Band and scenes from the half-time show at Michigan - Indiana football game. Features: William D. Revelli, UM-Music; George Cavender, UM-Music; Jerry Bilik, UM-Music
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #41, Pos. #634
  - Physical Medicine 1955, 851831-H-27; Chairman of the Dept. of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation at UM Hospital demonstrates the treatment and therapy used in care of physical injuries. Features: James Rae, UM-Hosp.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #42, Pos. #635
  - Michigan Week 1955, 851831-H-28; Members of the Cultural Activities Board of the Michigan Week celebration discuss Michigan authors, community theatre in Michigan, and amateur art in the state, folksinger Ed Banghart performs songs from the state's mining and lumbering era. Features: Robert Haugh, Hugh Norton, Mike Church, Ed Banghart, Carl Bond
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #43
  - Diploma - Special Delivery 1955, 851831-H-29; Director of the Correspondence Study Program of UM Extension Service describes the operation of the Correspondence Study Program. Features: Alfred Lee, UM-Extension
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #45, Pos. #637
  - On Target 1955, 851831-H-30; Members of the Women's Athletic Association Rifle Club of the University of Michigan discuss the activities of the club and demonstrate marksmanship. Gubbins, holder of two national records discusses her involvement in competitive shooting. Features: Roberta Gubbins; Nancy O'Toole
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #46
  - Gilbert and Sullivan 1955, 851831-H-31; A look at the Gilbert and Sullivan Society's rehearsal for a production of "Iolanthe" and a discussion of the group's activities. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Gilbert and Sullivan Society
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #51, Pos. #962
  - Michigan Week - Folksongs 1955, 851831-H-32; UM expert on folklore outlines the growth of folk music in Michigan, a UM student performs a number of Michigan folk songs. Features: Ivan Walton, UM-Engl.; Ed Banghart, UM-student
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #54, Pos. #965
  - School of Education: 75th Anniversary
    - History 1955, 851831-H-33-1; History.; Five part series commemorating the 75th anniversary of the UM School of Education. The history of the school is examined through documents, photos, and paintings. Features: Claude Eggertsen, UM-Ed.; Willard Olson, UM-Ed.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #55, Pos. #966
    - Buildings 1955, 851831-H-33-2; Buildings.; Professor of School Administration and building consultant tells how schools are being custom built to meet the needs of today's education. Features: Howard Jones, UM-Ed.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #56, Pos. #967
    - Physical Education 1955, 851831-H-33-3; Physical Education.; Program examines how the women's physical education program integrates recreational leadership and the cultural resources of a university into its training of teachers. Features: Elizabeth Ludwig, UM-Ed.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #57, Pos. #968
    - Mathematics 1955, 851831-H-33-4; Mathematics.; Mathematics and education methods professor discusses the teaching of mathematics, emphasizes mathematics' relationship to everyday life. Features: Philip Jones, UM-Ed.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #58, Pos. #969
    - The Teaching of Reading 1955, 851831-H-33-5; The Teaching of Reading.; UM professor advocates the merits of the "word recognition" method of teaching reading as opposed to the traditional "phonics" method, discusses the national controversy on the subject. Features: Irving Anderson, UM-Ed.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #59, Pos. #970
  - Imaginary Voyages 1955, 851831-H-34; The Hubbard Collection of Imaginary Voyages in the UM General Library Rare Book Room, Pearce discusses the origins of the collection donated by UM Regent Lucius L. Hubbard and Hymans shows several of the unique items. Features: Donald Pearce, UM-Engl.; Ella Hymans, Curator of Rare Books
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #60, Pos. #971
  - Ships Through the Seaway 1955, 851831-H-35; Chairman of the Canadian section of the International Joint Commission discusses the construction of the St. Lawrence Seaway and its potential impact on Michigan. Features: Gen. A.G.L. McNaughton
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #62, Pos. #973
  - Atom and You, The 1955, 851831-H-36; UM professor and electric company executive show how close acquaintance with peacetime atomic program can replace fear with hope in the public mind. Features: Ralph A. Sawyer, UM-Phoenix Project; Walker Cisler, Detroit Edison
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #63, Pos. #974
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 11)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-H36.flv
  - Best in Michigan Art, The 1955, 851831-H-37; Director of UM Museum of Art conducts gallery tour through 50 years of Michigan's best professional art. Features: Jean Paul Slusser, Dir. UM Museum of Art
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #64, Pos. #975
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 11)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-H37.flv
  - Words on the Wing 1955, 851831-H-38; Head of UM Extension Library discusses how important books and information reach libraries throughout the state. Features: Clover Flanders, UM-Extension
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #66, Pos. #977
  - Midac 1955, 851831-H-39; The story of the UM's highspeed electronic computer "Midac" built under the sponsorship of the U.S. Air Force. Features: John Corr, UM-Math.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #67, Pos. #978
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 11)
    - Streaming File:, 851831-H39.flv
  - Grand Tour 1955, 851831-H-40; Director and members of the UM Men's Glee Club relive some of the memorable experiences of their recent European concert tour. Features: Philip Duey, UM-Music
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #70, Pos. #981
  - Pursuit of Happiness, The 1955, 851831-H-41; Economist Philip Wernette predicts "fabulous" prosperity, personal security and increased leisure time for Americans in the next 50 years. Features: Philip Wernette, UM-Econ.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #74, Pos. #985
  - Behind the Footlights 1955, 851831-H-42; Wife of the director of the UM Musical Society relates anecdote about some of the famous musicians she has entertained at her home, comments on her role as hostess. Features: Mrs. Charles Sink
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #75, Pos. #343
  - Land Divers 1955, 851831-H-43; A UM student recounts his experiences as one of the first white men to view a rare ritual of the natives of Pentecost Island. During harvest festival men dive off an 84 ft tower with a vine tied to their leg to break the fall, landing on their heads Features: John Nelson
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #78, Pos. #980
  - Living Language 1955, 851831-H-44; Director of the UM's new combined program in foreign language instruction discusses modern methods of foreign language instruction. Features: Otto Graf, UM-Modern Lang.; James O'Neill, UM-Engl.
    - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, b/w sound, ca. 00:15:00, neg. #81, Pos. #990
  - Christmas Songs 1954, 851831-H-45; Delta Tau Delta fraternity choir, winner of an Interfraternity Council competition, sings Christmas carols. Features:
    - Original:
- Series S
  Series S, Special Projects, consists of a mix films and videotape produced or collected by the Television Center, but generally not intended for broadcast. Most were produced for, or in conjunction with, academic units.
  - Architecture and Design - Pine Knob Development., 851831-S-2; Program on urban planning and development produced for School of Architecture and Design professor Les Fader, examines the Pine Knob development in suburban Detroit.
    - Original:, 2-inch video, color, sound, ca. 30:00, Tape #582
  - Business School Interactive Video Project, 851831-S-4; Footage used in a University of Michigan School of Business Administration interactive video project. (Three one-inch tapes, nos. 631-633.)
    - Original:, 2-inch video #631-633
  - CRLT: Math
    - CRLT: Math, 851831-S-5-1; An Introduction to Differential Geometry.; Seven part instructional film produced by the UM-TVC in cooperation with the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching Features: Noel Hicks, UM-Math
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #353, Pos. #228, 2-inch video #377
    - CRLT: Math, 851831-S-5-2; Vector Fields and Curves.; Lesson two in the series "An Introduction to Differential Geometry." Features: Noel Hicks, UM-Math
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #354, Pos. #229, 2-inch video #378
    - CRLT: Math, 851831-S-5-3; Curves continued.; Lesson 3 of "An Introduction to Differential Geometry." Features: Noel Hicks, UM-Math
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #355, Pos. #230, 2-inch video #379
    - CRLT: Math, 851831-S-5-4; Integral Curves of Vector Fields. Lesson 4 of "An Introduction to Differential Geometry." Features: Noel Hicks, UM-Math
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #356, Pos. #231, 2-inch video #380
    - CRLT: Math, 851831-S-5-5; Covariant Differentiation.; Lesson 5 of "An Introduction to Differential Geometry." Features: Noel Hicks, UM-Math
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #356, Pos. #232, 2-inch video #381
    - CRLT: Math, 851831-S-5-6; Invariants of a Surface.; Lesson 6 of "An Introduction to Differential Geometry." Features: Noel Hicks, UM-Math
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #357, Pos. #233, 2-inch video #382
    - CRLT: Math, 851831-S-5-7; The Gauss Equation and Geodesics on a Surface.; Lesson 7 of "An Introduction to Differential Geometry." Features: Noel Hicks, UM-Math
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #358, Pos. #234, 2-inch video #383
  - CRLT: Strength of Solids
    - Imperfect Crystals, 851831-S-6-1; Imperfect Crystals.; Parts of a series on the crystal structure of metals produced by the UM-TVC for the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching and the Department of Mechanical Engineering. Features: David Felback, UM-Eng.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #360, Pos. #235
    - Perfect Crystals, 851831-S-6-2; Perfect Crystals.; Lesson 2 of the series "Strength of Solids." Features: David Felback, UM-Eng.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #361, Pos. #236
    - Phase Boundary, 851831-S-6-3; Phase Boundary.; Lesson 3 of the series "Strength of Solids." (Short segment at the beginning of the film is defective.) Features: David Felback, UM-Eng.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #362, Pos. #237
    - Strengthening Mechanisms, 851831-S-6-4; Strengthening Mechanisms.; Lesson 4 of the series "Strength of Solids." Features: David Felback, UM-Eng.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #363, Pos. #239
    - CRLT: Strength of Solids, 851831-S-6-5; Features: David Felback, UM-Eng.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #364
    - Introduction to Mechanism, 851831-S-6-6
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #365, Pos. #238
  - Campaign for Michigan, 851831-S-7; Training and promotional film for workers in the University of Michigan fund-raising effort "Campaign for Michigan." (One-inch tape no. 626.)
    - Original:, 1-inch video #626
  - DRDA (Division of Research Development and Administration), 851831-S-9; Unedited material for UM-DRDA production on research activity and support at UM. Includes shots of UM campus and offices and laboratories of a number of Ann Arbor corporate offices and laboratories. (Two one-inch tapes, nos. 612-613.)
    - Original:, 2-inch video #612
  - EPA/SNR, 851831-S-10; Production material and unedited footage for project sponsored by the Environmental Protection Agency and the UM School of Natural resources. (Three one-inch tapes, nos. 634-635, 645.)
    - Original:, 2-inch video #635
  - Engineering Promotional Footage
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-1; Original footage shot for an Engineering College Promotional show, includes shots of campus, engineering facilities, an interview with James Duderstadt, industrial footage, "A" and "B" rolls of the final production, and film to tape Features: James Duderstadt, UM-Eng.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #586
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-1; transfers of several commercially produce industrial films.
      - Original:
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-2; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #587
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-3; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #588
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-4; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #589
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-5; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #590
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-6; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #591
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-7; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #592
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-8; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #593
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-9; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #594
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-10; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #595
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-11; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #596
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-12; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film. Includes transfer of the film "Energy in Harmony."
      - Original:, 2-inch video #597
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-13; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film. Includes transfer of 16mm film "The Link."
      - Original:, 2-inch video #598
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-14; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film. Includes transfer of the 16mm film "Robots, Unigraphics, tapping the Source."
      - Original:, 2-inch video #600
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-15; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #599
    - Engineering Promo, 851831-S-11-16; Additional footage for College of Engineering promotional film.
      - Original:, 2-inch video #601
  - Engineering School Fund Raising 1976, 851831-S-13; Program for use at meetings of UM Engineering Alumni. Three alums join Howe and Rugone in discussion of capital campaign to upgrade campus engineering facilities. Footage of old labs and North Campus sites. Fleming discusses development plans. Features: Robert Howe, UM-Eng.; Robben Fleming, UM-Pres.; Dave Rugone, UM-Eng.
    - Original:, 16mm film, Pos. #3405 (also 3/4-inch tape B35-B38)
  - Fairlane Announcement, 851831-S-14; Footage of Henry Ford, II making transfer of Fairlane Mansion to the University of Michigan. Features: Harlan Hatcher, UM-Pres.; Henry Ford, II
    - Original:, 1-inch video, b/w, sound, ca. 30:00, Tape #572
  - Ford Library Conference of the Presidency and Foreign Policy, 851831-S-16; Coverage of a conference held at the Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library on the presidency and foreign policy. (Three one-inch tapes, nos. 628-630.)
    - Original:, 2-inch video #628
  - Ford/UAW/SPH, 851831-S-17; Source footage for a program on the handling of caustic and hazardous material sponsored by Ford Motor Co., the United Auto Workers, and UM School of Public Health, includes footage from Ford's Rawsonville plant. (Three one-inch tapes, nos. 642-645.)
    - Original:, 2-inch video #642
  - Full Circle, 851831-S-18
    - Original:, 2-inch video, Tape #536
  - G.R. Garrison Television Studio Dedication
    - G.R. Garrison Dedication, 851831-S-19-1; Footage of a "roast" of Garnet Garrison on the occasion of his retirement. Hazen Schumacher hosts, speakers include many current and former employees of the UM television studios. Features: Garnet Garrison, UM-Speech; Hazen Schumacher, UM-TVC
      - Original:, cassette #M174
    - G.R. Garrison Dedication, 851831-S-19-2; Continues the "roast" of Garnet Garrison on the occasion of his retirement. Features: Garnet Garrsion, UM-Speech; Hazen Schumacher, UM-TVC
      - Original:, cassette #M175
    - G.R. Garrison Dedication (Personal Messages To G.R.G.), 851831-S-20; Personal menages to Garnet Garrison from television center staff and friends on the occasion of his retirement.
      - Original:, cassette #M173
  - Hazen's Campus Slide Show, 851831-S-24; Two-inch videotape of a slide show depicting University of Michigan campus buildings, personalities and events. Produced by Hazen Schumacher.
    - Original:, 2-inch videotape
  - Jackson State Prison footage
    - Jackson State Prison 1977, 851831-S-25-1; Footage shot at the State Prison of Southern Michigan in Jackson for use in the Series B program "Medicine Behind Bars." Includes pan shots of the prison grounds, mess hall, kitchen and other facilities, brief interviews with inmates and guards.
      - Original:, cassette #B120
    - Jackson State Prison 1977, 851831-S-25-2; Continues footage of Jackson State Prison.
      - Original:, cassette #B121
    - Jackson State Prison 1977, 851831-S-25-3; Continues footage of Jackson State Prison.
      - Original:, cassette #B122
    - Jackson State Prison 1977, 851831-S-25-4; Continues footage of Jackson State Prison.
      - Original:, cassette #B123
  - M Capsule - University of Michigan, 851831-S-26; Raw footage for promotional film for the University of Michigan aimed at prospective students. For Office of Undergraduate Admission.
    - Original:
    - Use copy:, DVD (Box 14)
  - Magazine Segments
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-27; Short filler segments produced for WDIV-TV. Some of these were later used in the Series B "Phenomenon" programs. (No. 549-553 are two inch tapes. No. 554-559 are one-inch tapes labeled "Masters," 560-662 are one-inch tapes, some possibly duplicates.)
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-1; These programs appear to be the same as the Series B "Phenomenon" programs.
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-2
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-3
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-4
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-5
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-6
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-7
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-8
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-9
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-10
      - Original:
    - Magazine Segments, 851831-S-28-11
      - Original:
  - Michigan Media Christmas Show
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1960-1963, 851831-S-34-1; Two-inch videotape of a Christmas show put on by members of the Michigan media staff. (Tape #537)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1964, 851831-S-34-2; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #524)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1965, 851831-S-34-3; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #525)
      - Original:, Pos. #957
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1967, 851831-S-34-4; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #526)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1968, 851831-S-34-5; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #527)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1971, 851831-S-34-6; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #528)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1972, 851831-S-34-7; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #529)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1973, 851831-S-34-8; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #530)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1974, 851831-S-34-9; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #531)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1975, 851831-S-34-10; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by members of Michigan Media staff. (Tape #532)
      - Original:
    - Michigan Media Christmas Show 1976, 851831-S-34-11; Two-inch videotape of Christmas show put on by Michigan Media staff members. (Tape #533)
      - Original:
  - Michigan Media Live
    - Michigan Media Live 1982, 851831-S-35-1; (One-inch tape no. 621.)
      - Original:, 2-inch video #621
    - Michigan Media Live 1982, 851831-S-35-2; (One-inch tape no. 622.)
      - Original:, 2-inch video #622
    - Michigan Media Live 1982, 851831-S-35-3; (One-inch tape no. 623.)
      - Original:, 2-inch video #623
    - Michigan Media Live 1982, 851831-S-35-4; (One-inch tape no. 624)
      - Original:, 2-inch video #624
  - Music School Promo, 851831-S-36; Edited master for a UM School of Music promotional tape. (One-inch tape no. 617.)
    - Original:, 2-inch video #617
  - Office of Communications 1987, 851831-S-39; Interviews with University of Michigan students. (One-inch tape no. 627.)
    - Original:, 2-inch video #627
  - President Fleming Inaugural Announcement 1968, 851831-S-40; Two inch videotape of CBS(?) produced newsclip on the inauguration of Pres. Fleming, March 11, 1968. (Tape #569) Features: Robben Fleming, UM-Pres.
    - Original:, 2-inch video, Tape #569
  - Robert Frost Live Remote From Hill Auditorium, 851831-S-42; Documentary footage of a lecture, poetry reading by Robert Frost. (This was produced for the MPATI series "Franklin to Frost." Duplication of this program is restricted. Obtain permission from MPATI and the Frost estate.) Features: Robert Frost